Meeting Highlights transforms lengthy Teams meetings into dynamic, bite-sized video recaps, allowing users to quickly catch up on what matters most.
Combining AI-generated voiceover summaries with authentic video snippets, it captures important moments while preserving the original tone and flow.
Thanks to this approach, users can review key topics and the overall meeting atmosphere without having to watch the entire recording.
Developing meeting highlights was a complex collaboration across Microsoft.
ODSP handled back and streaming and storage.
MSAI Hive led content generation and scenario ownership, while Clipchamp and Loop enabled playback.
BizChat and Teams provide easy access for users.
Let's take a closer look at how backend systems orchestrate the process of generating meeting highlights.
When a Teams meeting recording finishes, a backend event is triggered.
This event initiates the highlight generation workflow.
The textual transcription of the meeting is sent directly to a large language model, which analyzes the content to identify key moments and topics.
The model returns a structured list of textual metadata objects, with each representing a highlight.
Highlights fall into two categories: abstractive, which provides succinct summaries of discussion topics, and key moments, which pinpoint significant points in the original meeting.
Each highlight includes unique timestamps covering 20- to 30-second segments and a narration text that summarizes the key content.
This narration text is then converted into audio using Azure Cognitive Services.
Once generated, all highlight metadata, timestamps, narrated audio, and captions are securely stored in OneDrive SharePoint ODSP.
This approach ensures that the highlights are readily available to various platforms like M365 Chat, Clipchamp Web, and the team's recap page.
Importantly, the process does not create any new video files only metadata is generated and stored, providing efficient access to key meeting moments across Microsoft 365 without additional storage overhead.
Cost efficiency while maintaining quality is critical for scaling meeting highlights globally.
The initial implementation required 4 sequential LLM calls per meeting, creating significant computational costs.
The first prompt segmented transcripts into one to seven key topics.
The second prompt extracted up to 10 self-contained utterance blocks capturing key feedback, news, or demonstrations.
The third prompt ranked utterance blocks by quality, clarity, intelligibility, self-containment, and interest.
The 4th prompt synthesized A cohesive narrative with smooth transitions between abstractive and extractive sections.
We collapsed the four-step pipeline into one unified prompt with leaner input.
Dedicated tuning preserved the original algorithm as an internal reasoning chain: segment, extract, rank, compose.
The model executes this sequence in a single invocation instead of four external calls.
We trimmed input size significantly for lower cost.
Separate tuning adapted the model to the slimmer schema and token budget while maintaining valid output for video generation.
75% fewer model invocations per meeting.
GPU requirements dropped from 600 to 200 for global availability.
This cut COGS by over 50%, enabling economically viable worldwide rollout.
The unified prompt produces higher-quality highlights.
Internal reviewers strongly prefer it over the multi-prompt version.
These improvements unblock private preview and enable general availability within capacity constraints.
The meeting highlights feature has received overwhelmingly positive feedback in a recent Ms.
Elite survey, underscoring its growing impact and daily use among our users.
More than 80% of users rated meeting highlights as extremely useful or very useful.
In addition, 96% shared that they are very likely or likely to use the feature again, pointing to strong product market fit and daily habit formation.
Users have shared enthusiastic feedback.
Kevin C commented, Love this feature.
Great way to catch up on a recap without watching the full thing.
Ryan Roslonsky added, Beyond the awesome text recap.
There is literally a two-minute narrated video about the meeting.
It's mind-blowing and an engaging way to recap a meeting for a richer understanding of the conversation.
While the core experience is resonating, users also expressed valuable requests for improvement.
Suggestions include making highlights more detailed and specific, integrating highlights more directly into Teams Recap, including action items, and supporting additional languages.